<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-12-05T09:03:40+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>ADD DESCRIPTION HERE
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">XYX</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/xyx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="XYX" /><published>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/xyx</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/xyx/"><![CDATA[<h3>XYXY</h3><p>jjjjjjj</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=a910259283f3" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-perception-gap" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[XYXYjjjjjjj]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI Perception Gap: From Tragedy to Closure—How AI Identified Plane Crash Victims</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/apg-blog-01/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Perception Gap: From Tragedy to Closure—How AI Identified Plane Crash Victims" /><published>2024-11-19T08:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-19T08:40:16+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/apg-blog-01</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/apg-blog-01/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-story-behind-the-crash">The Story Behind The Crash</h2>

<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>

<p>On July 17, 2014, a Malaysian Airways passenger jet was shot down on its journey from Amsterdam Schiphol Airport to Kuala Lumpur. The plane was flying through Ukrainian airspace, 50 km from the Russian border, when it was struck by a surface-to-air missile over a region controlled by Russian-backed separatists during the war in Donbas. 298 victims were tragically killed. Identifying and returning body parts to loved ones was a formidable challenge as unidentified human remains (UHR) were dispersed over a 50 square kilometre region. Meanwhile, heartbroken families across the globe were grieving. Aware that each passing day without a body to bury only added to the immense trauma the deceased’s families were experiencing, investigators looked to AI to help with returning UHR to loved ones as quickly as possible.</p>

<h3 id="the-challenges">The Challenges</h3>

<p>Investigators at the Netherlands Forensic Institute (NFI) were tasked with the difficult identification process. Frustratingly, they faced a number of obstacles.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>DNA quality</strong>: Fire and explosions during the crash meant remains were heavily burned, thereby degrading DNA.</li>
  <li><strong>Site accessibility</strong>: The remains were spread across an active war zone which presented obvious accessibility issues. Body parts continued to arrive in the Netherlands for 10 months.</li>
  <li><strong>DNA history</strong>: The investigators did not have previous records of the victims’ DNA, simply because they were not criminals! Identification had to be performed by DNA comparison with relatives. DNA donations were limited in some cases due to the death of immediate family in the crash or a lack of contact with other family members.</li>
  <li><strong>Volume</strong>: When matching body parts by DNA comparison, the number of necessary comparisons is about the square of the number of body parts that need to be identified. 10 victims in a Blue Wing Airlines crash on April 3, 2008, were identified by 100 manual DNA comparisons. This took 2 days by hand. However, investigators at NFI were forced to make upwards of 90000 comparisons for 298 victims. Comparisons by hand were simply infeasible.</li>
</ol>

<p>The investigators needed a comparison-based identification framework that offered flexibility in terms of the number of DNA donations and the relationship of the donor. Most importantly, the system had to perform identifications as fast as possible!</p>

<h3 id="the-solution">The Solution</h3>

<p>Fortunately for the NFI, they had a state-of-the-art forensic software system - named Bonaparte - developed by a team at Radboud University in Nijmegen, Netherlands, during the mid-2000s. The system, which was designed to facilitate quick human DNA-based identification, was the perfect solution for the investigation as it overcame the challenges presented above. It enabled the identification of body parts even in the limited setting of partial DNA matches due to fires; it facilitated DNA donations from multiple family members with great flexibility offered in terms of relationship with the victim (the more distant the relation, the less similar the DNA); and the digital nature of the system permitted 1000s of DNA comparisons in minutes.</p>

<p>After analysing 6,000+ UHR body fragments and 500+ reference samples from relatives, 294 of the 298 victims had been identified within four months of the crash. Another two victims have since been identified, whilst the remaining two have sadly vanished without a trace.</p>

<h2 id="the-technology">The Technology</h2>

<h3 id="identification-by-cause-and-effect">Identification by Cause and Effect</h3>

<p>Consider the sentence: “10-year-old Ben Barlow hit the football towards his grandparents’ window and the window smashed.” Much to the annoyance of my grandad, who was enjoying his 70th birthday at the time, this statement is true. After observing the cause (Ben kicks the ball), we can estimate the probability of the effect (the window smashed). Human cognition works in this direction.</p>

<p>But, given the effect “the window smashed” (and my grandad spent the afternoon of his birthday boarding up a window whilst all the family went out to celebrate), we need much more information to deduce the cause (who kicked the ball that broke it or even the fact that it was broken by a ball in the first place). Human cognition struggles to work in this direction.</p>

<p>This cognitive asymmetry was overcome in the 1700s when theologian Thomas Bayes proposed a new rule to employ when working with probabilies. Using the rule - now known as Bayes’ Theorem - one can work in the natural cognitive direction by estimating the probability of the effect given the cause, and use mathematical tools to infer the probability of the cause having observed the effect. We call this “inverse probability”.</p>

<p>Now, in the context of identifying human remains: If person A and person B are the mother and father of person C (the cause), then matches will exist if we compare the DNA of the child with its parents (the effect). Expanding on the network of three nodes and two arrows (two parents, one child, with an arrow for each parent-child relationship), Bonparte built much bigger networks (entire family trees). This permitted DNA donations from cousins, aunts, and other relatives, rather than just being limited to donations from parents. When comparing all relations, Bonparte was given the effect and used inverse probability to determine the probability of the cause.</p>

<p>A single UHR fragment was identified by the investigators by iterating through all 298 pedigree trees built using Bonparte, entering the fragment’s DNA into each tree and observing the probability of the cause given the effect. By considering the trees that offered the maximal probability of the cause, the body part could be identified.</p>

<h3 id="the-story-behind-the-technology-how-neuroscience-can-inspire-ai">The Story Behind The Technology: How Neuroscience Can Inspire AI</h3>

<p>Bonparte proved to be an indispensable tool for the investigators. It offered flexibility in the number of DNA donations and the relationship of the donor whilst possessing the ability to infer the probability of the cause after being provided the effect. This was all made possible by the technology that underpinned Bonparte: Bayesian networks.</p>

<p>Over two centuries after Thomas Bayes’ (1702 - 1761) work on cause and effect, along came Israeli-American computer scientist and philosopher Judea Pearl (1936 - present). Whilst you may not be familiar with Pearl, you’ve likely heard the phrase “correlation, not causation”. Pearl spent his academic career developing mathematical tools for causal reasoning; we can now make “X causes Y” conclusions rather than being limited to “X correlates with Y”. During his academic journey, Pearl invented Bayesian networks and because of their dependence on inverse probability, Pearl honoured Bayes by naming the framework after him.</p>

<p>Pearl’s breakthrough was a prime example of how neuroscience can inspire AI. His eureka moment came in the mid-80s whilst reading an article by David Rumelhart: a cognitive scientist at University of California, San Diego. The article highlighted when humans read, we first recognise lines and circles which we combine to form letters; these combine to form words at the lexical level which are passed to the syntactic level. It is here, for example, that we decide to expect a noun to follow the word “the”. Finally, we reach the semantic level, where we remember the previous sentence referenced a Volkswagen, so we predict the noun following “the” could be “car”. Climbing the ladder is permitted by information moving through layers of neurons in the brain.</p>

<p>All the while, information gets propagated down the neural ladder too. When we struggle to read poor handwriting, the syntactic and semantic levels provide context, which helps us recognise messy shapes, letters, and words. The key here is neurons in the brain are passing information in both directions (from the top down and the bottom up) and from side to side. A change in belief in one neuron has the ability to affect the state of all other neurons.</p>

<p>Pearl was convinced, that for computers to reason well under uncertainty, they must adopt a structure similar to that of human neural information processing. It took Pearl a few months to figure out that messages between layers should consist of forward probabilities and inverse probabilities computed using Bayes’ framework. But, by the end of the 1980s, his students and colleagues had helped him create a tool that would accelerate the world of machine learning.</p>

<p>in 2011, Pearl won the Turing Award - the highest distinction in computer science - for “fundamental contributions to artificial intelligence through the development of a calculus for probabilistic and causal reasoning”. Without his contributions, the field of AI would be lacking many of the tools it has available today, and the families of the plane crash victims would likely have waited much longer to bury their loved ones, or not even been able to bury them at all.</p>

<h2 id="appendix---a-note-on-ai">Appendix - A Note On AI</h2>

<p>As discussed in Introducing my blog: AI (para mis amigos), my goal is to close the <em>AI perception gap</em>. Whilst I was writing this blog in Valencia in June 2023, my flatmate asked “artificial intelligence isn’t here yet, is it?” Well, I walked past a sign in my department this week, which read “Celebrating 60 years of research in computer science and AI at the University of Edinburgh”. AI has been around for a long time, and Bayesian networks are an example of 1980s technology still being state-of-the-art today!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-perception-gap" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Plane crash investigators identify 6000+ human fragments by harnessing neuroscience-inspired AI and centuries-old mathematics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My MSc Dissertation Project at Stanford University</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-msc-dissertation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My MSc Dissertation Project at Stanford University" /><published>2024-11-18T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-18T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-msc-dissertation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-msc-dissertation/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Well, that was the coolest professional experience of my life…</strong></p>

<h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>

<p>From delving into AI and critical minerals research with world-class experts to gatecrashing conferences littered with talent, my three weeks at Stanford were a whirlwind of fun and academic growth. Add in the California sunshine and a road trip in a convertible Mustang, and you’ve got the recipe for an unforgettable academic adventure.</p>

<h2 id="pre-stanford">Pre-Stanford</h2>

<p>How on Earth did I–an AI student at the University of Edinburgh–end up spending the first three weeks of my dissertation working with academics on Stanford University’s campus?</p>

<p>It all kicked off with a lightbulb moment a year earlier. There I was, lounging on the sofa, when it hit me: I’d be investing hundreds of hours into a project next summer anyway, so why not aim high? If I could find a company or research group I was extrmely passionate about, I could use my three month project as a trial period for a dream job or PhD, thereby informing my subsequent life decisions.</p>

<p>Fired up by this idea, I dove into research mode. After a week of looking far and wide, I struck gold: Silicon Valley startup KoBold Metals. Their mission to leverage data science for accelerating mineral discoveries had me absolutely captivated.</p>

<p>But the real jackpot? Discovering their academic research partner, Mineral-X at Stanford University, had a team member who’d previously studied in Edinburgh. I knew I’d found my perfect supervisor!</p>

<p>Fast forward through a winter of persistent emails and video calls, and by summer, I’d lined up my a dream dissertation project in a topic that excited me at a world-leading university. A project marrying two fields; applying an AI technique to the domain mineral exploration for the critical battery metals. Determined to squeeze every drop of opportunity from this chance, I self-funded a 3-week trip to California.</p>

<h2 id="my-time-at-stanford">My Time at Stanford</h2>

<p>The experience was truly exceptional. AI research lab SISL, who provide AI technical support to Mineral-X, provided a warm welcome, offering me a desk in their office. As a master’s student working on only my second ever research project, being surrounded by Stanford PhDs and post-docs was incredibly special.</p>

<p>Having access to world experts in POMDPs (the AI technique I was using) proved invaluable. Their on-demand, in-person guidance significantly accelerated my progress. Beyond the office, they were lovely people too; kindly involving me in weekly ultimate frisbee, taking me to rock up and play soccer games with their friends, and freeing up time to go for coffee/beer to chat in a relaxed setting.</p>

<p>Beyond the academics I worked with directly, I met some incredible people too. During my first week, I was thrilled to discover Mineral-X were hosting their annual symposium during my second week on campus. This gathering brought together industry leaders, heads of data science teams, and recent PhD graduates from around the world, all in one place. The opportunity to engage directly with such a diverse group of experts in my field of interest was truly invaluable.</p>

<p>Besides the professional gains, June in California is somewhat superior to June in Edinburgh. Downtime was spent enjoying rounds at Stanford University Golf Course or supporting the Three Lions in the European Championships at a local English pub. To conclude the trip, I took a two-day Top Gear style drive drifting across both lanes of empty roads with amazing views in a convertible Mustang. I explored San Francisco’s bustling streets; crossed the Golden Gate Bridge; snapped pictures of Bay Area views; and rounded it off by drinking a bottle of red from Sonoma Valley in Sonoma Valley itself.</p>

<h2 id="reflection">Reflection</h2>

<p>I’ve ticked off a number of typical achievements in my life: from graduating school with the maximal grade of 3 A*s to being elected by my peers as 1st XI captain of the University of Warwick Men’s Football Club. But, sporting and academic achievements had never brought a sense of immense pride. After all, there is always someone outperforming you in academia and I’ve played alongside teammates far more talented footballers than me.</p>

<p>But, I know no one who had the initative to set up a dissertation project that aligned with their passions with an external supervisor based at a world-leading university they were not enrolled at. This time, my experience was entirely unique, and the sense of pride was striking.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A reflective blog on my dissertation project, in-particular my three week trip to California.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI Perception Gap: Introducing my new blog!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/apg-00/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Perception Gap: Introducing my new blog!" /><published>2024-11-17T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/apg-00</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/apg-00/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>A blog created to change Gen Z’s perception of artificial intelligence and its applications.</strong></p>

<h2 id="motivation">Motivation?</h2>

<p>While traveling in Latin America during the summer of 2022, I became deeply aware of what I call the <strong>“AI perception gap”</strong>. For 5 weeks, I listened to AI-oriented podcasts by day - on treacherous bus journeys, sea-side sunbeds and rainforest-based hammocks - and socialised in hostel bars by night. From sunrise to sunset, my ears were flooded with hope, optimism, and trust in AI. After dark, however, I was inundated with negativity from backpacker after backpacker - irrespective of nationality. “Do you love Elon Musk?” “When are we all losing our jobs then, mate?” “I’ll blame you when the robots take over!” All are exclamations I heard in abundance when I told new friends my plan to pursue an MSc in Artificial Intelligence upon my return.</p>

<p>I honestly could not believe my ears. Educated individuals, from my very generation (not my grandparents!), who were born and raised in wealthy economies where AI is booming, and no one had a clue about the monumental positive impact the technology can and will have on society at a global scale! The perception gap was born…</p>

<h2 id="purpose">Purpose?</h2>

<p>Fix the perception gap! I did so on an individual level in hostel bar after hostel bar during my travels. (Surprisingly, this didn’t make me the life of the party!) But with a blog, I can have a much more significant impact!</p>

<p>The overarching aim is to <strong>educate, inspire, and change the perception</strong> of AI. I will highlight use cases of AI that are having a positive impact on society. If all goes to plan, the audience will learn that “AI” does not equate to “self-modifying systems (code-writing code) that are destined to take over the world and kill us all”.</p>

<h2 id="audience">Audience?</h2>

<p>For my friends! The blog is for my friends. The translation, of course, acts as a constant reminder of my Latin American experience which inspired the blog. More specifically, “my friends” corresponds to educated individuals (educated to degree level in a different discipline), from all over the world, with ages ranging from 18 to 30.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-ai">What is AI?</h2>

<p>AI. I hear it all the time! It’s become a buzzword every business seems to throw on its social channels in an attempt to gain traction.</p>

<p>For the purpose of this blog, I will not cross hairs about specific AI sub-fields. Like seemingly every business out there - if there is cool machine learning, data science, deep learning, statistics, or one of many other subfields being used under the hood — I will just call it AI (see appendix for sub-field definitions).</p>

<h2 id="enjoy">Enjoy!</h2>

<p>Feel free to engage with comments or by reaching out!</p>

<p>In keeping with my Latin American theme, my first blog will discuss a story I learned of whilst reading Judea Pearl’s <em>The Book of Why</em> on a beanbag in a hostel atrium in San Cristobal, Mexico. Read here how artificial intelligence permitted the rapid return of human remains to their families following a plane shooting above the Russia-Ukraine border in 2014.</p>

<h2 id="negative-impacts-of-ai">Negative impacts of AI</h2>

<p>It must be noted that I am aware that AI has the potential to impact society negatively. Many pro-AI folks are blind to its destructive potential. Of course, risks exist! But, a plethora of risks didn’t stop the internet from booming a few decades ago. Adopters of the technology just learned to spot the risks (for example, online scams). I hope we’ll do the same as AI becomes more and more prevalent in society.</p>

<h2 id="appendix">Appendix</h2>

<h3 id="ai-sub-fields">AI sub-fields</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Field</th>
      <th>Definition</th>
      <th>Example</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Machine Learning (ML)</td>
      <td>Systems that learn patterns in data, enabling predictions about future data.</td>
      <td>Insurance companies predicting the probability of you crashing your car based on your age, make, model, gender, and more.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Deep Learning</td>
      <td>A subset of machine learning that utilises complicated <em>artificial neural networks</em>.</td>
      <td>Same as above.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Natural Language Processing (NLP)</td>
      <td>Focuses on understanding, interpreting, and generating human language.</td>
      <td>Translation from one language to another.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Computer Vision</td>
      <td>Focuses on interpreting and understanding the visual world.</td>
      <td>A self-driving car.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Reinforcement Learning</td>
      <td>A system that learns to make decisions by taking actions in an environment to achieve a reward.</td>
      <td>An AI that plays chess 1000s of times and learns optimal strategies by trial and error.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Generative AI</td>
      <td>Systems that are capable of creating content (for example, text, images, music).</td>
      <td>Deepfakes that can generate realistic but entirely fictional video content. ChatGPT.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="ai-related-fields">AI-related fields</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Field</th>
      <th>Definition</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Data Science</td>
      <td>An interdisciplinary field that aims to extract knowledge and insights from structured and unstructured data. It combines aspects of statistics, mathematics, and computer science.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Statistics</td>
      <td>A branch of mathematics dealing with the collection, analysis, interpretation, presentation, and organization of data. It provides a framework for making inferences about the characteristics or behaviors of groups or phenomena based on a finite set of observations.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="other-definitions">Other definitions</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Field</th>
      <th>Definition</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Artificial Neural network</td>
      <td>A computational model inspired by the way biological neural networks in the human brain work. It aims to spot patterns in data, much like our brain learned to spot patterns in auditory data when we learned to speak as a baby.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-perception-gap" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A blog created to change Gen Z's perception of artificial intelligence and its applications.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Test Blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-test-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Test Blog" /><published>2024-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-test-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-test-blog/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a temporary blog to test the embedding of Medium articles on my website.</p><p>This is here</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=55af3372fa3c" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a temporary blog to test the embedding of Medium articles on my website.This is here]]></summary></entry></feed>