<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-12-05T18:09:09+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>ADD DESCRIPTION HERE
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">AI Perception Gap: Introducing my new blog!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/ai-perception-gap-introducing-my-new-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Perception Gap: Introducing my new blog!" /><published>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/ai-perception-gap-introducing-my-new-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/ai-perception-gap-introducing-my-new-blog/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>A blog created to educate, inspire, and reshape Gen Z’s perception of artificial intelligence and its applications.</strong></p><h3>Discovering the AI Perception Gap</h3><p>While backpacking Latin America during the summer of 2022, I became deeply aware of what I labelled the <em>AI perception gap</em><strong><em>. </em></strong>For 5 weeks, I listened to AI-oriented podcasts by day — on treacherous bus journeys, sea-side sunbeds and rainforest-based hammocks — and socialised in hostel bars by night. My ears were flooded with hope, optimism, and trust in AI from sunrise to sunset. After dark, however, I was inundated with negativity from backpacker after backpacker — irrespective of nationality. “<strong>Do you love Elon Musk?</strong>” “When are we all losing our jobs then, mate?” “I’ll blame you when the robots take over!” All are exclamations I heard in abundance when I told new friends my plan to pursue an MSc in Artificial Intelligence upon my return to the UK.</p><p>I honestly could not believe my ears. Educated individuals, from my very generation (not my grandparents!), who were born and raised in wealthy economies where AI is booming, and no one had a clue about the monumental positive impact the technology can and will have on society at a global scale! <strong>The perception gap was born…</strong></p><figure style="text-align: center;"><img width="90%" alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*WRDbSbGiMcOjXoi3WUmSlA.jpeg" /></figure><h3>Addressing the AI Perception Gap</h3><p>What is the aim of my blog? Fix the perception gap by making my friends aware of the positive potential of AI!</p><p>I did so on an individual level in hostel bar after hostel bar during my travels. (Surprisingly, this didn’t make me the life of the party!) But with a blog, I can have a much more significant impact!</p><p>The overarching aim is to <strong>educate, inspire, and reshape Gen Z’s perception</strong>. I will highlight use cases of AI that have a positive impact on society (and some negatively impacting use cases too). If all goes to plan, the audience will learn that “AI” does not equate to “self-modifying systems (code-writing code) that are destined to take over the world and kill us all”.</p><h3>Blog’s Target Audience</h3><p><strong>For my friends!</strong> More specifically, “my friends” correspond to <strong>educated individuals</strong> (educated to degree level in a <strong>different discipline</strong>), from all over the world, with ages ranging from <strong>18 to 30</strong>.</p><h3>What is AI?</h3><p>AI. I hear it all the time! It’s become a buzzword every business seems to throw on its social channels in an attempt to gain traction.</p><p>For this blog, I will not cross hairs about specific AI sub-fields. Like seemingly every business out there — if there is cool machine learning, data science, deep learning, statistics, or one of many other subfields being used under the hood — I will just call it AI. Essentially, I will term any system that sits in the Venn diagram below “AI”.</p><figure style="text-align: center;"><img width="90%" alt="" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1024/1*jTox5PBdB7tonTosN0Oy8w.png" /><figcaption >Image credit: Dr. Amy McGovern, the University of Oklahoma. See <a href="https://ai-fall2023.ai2es.org/module-1-overview/module-1-ltopic-1/">here</a>.</figcaption></figure><h3>Let’s Begin</h3><p>Initially, I will post exactly <strong>one blog a month on the 6th of each month for 6 months</strong>. Starting 6th December 2024 and finishing 6th May 2025 (my birthday!).</p><p>In keeping with my Latin American theme, my first blog will discuss a story I discovered whilst reading Judea Pearl’s <em>The Book of Why</em> on a beanbag in a hostel atrium in San Cristobal, Mexico. I will discuss how artificial intelligence permitted the rapid return of human remains to their families following a plane shooting above the Russia-Ukraine border in 2014.</p><h3>Negative impacts of AI</h3><p>It must be noted that I am aware that AI has the potential to impact society negatively. Many pro-AI folks are blind to its destructive potential. Of course, risks exist! But, a plethora of risks didn’t stop the internet from booming a few decades ago. Adopters of the technology just learned to spot the risks (for example, online scams). I hope we’ll do the same as AI becomes more prevalent in society.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=c2f12b136007" alt="">]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ai-perception-gap" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing a blog that educates, inspires, and reshapes Gen Z’s perception of artificial intelligence.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My MSc Dissertation Project at Stanford University</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-msc-dissertation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My MSc Dissertation Project at Stanford University" /><published>2024-11-18T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-18T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-msc-dissertation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/my-msc-dissertation/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Well, that was the coolest professional experience of my life…</strong></p>

<h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>

<p>From delving into AI and critical minerals research with world-class experts to gatecrashing conferences littered with talent, my three weeks at Stanford were a whirlwind of fun and academic growth. Add in the California sunshine and a road trip in a convertible Mustang, and you’ve got the recipe for an unforgettable academic adventure.</p>

<h2 id="pre-stanford">Pre-Stanford</h2>

<p>How on Earth did I–an AI student at the University of Edinburgh–end up spending the first three weeks of my dissertation working with academics on Stanford University’s campus?</p>

<p>It all kicked off with a lightbulb moment a year earlier. There I was, lounging on the sofa, when it hit me: I’d be investing hundreds of hours into a project next summer anyway, so why not aim high? If I could find a company or research group I was extrmely passionate about, I could use my three month project as a trial period for a dream job or PhD, thereby informing my subsequent life decisions.</p>

<p>Fired up by this idea, I dove into research mode. After a week of looking far and wide, I struck gold: Silicon Valley startup KoBold Metals. Their mission to leverage data science for accelerating mineral discoveries had me absolutely captivated.</p>

<p>But the real jackpot? Discovering their academic research partner, Mineral-X at Stanford University, had a team member who’d previously studied in Edinburgh. I knew I’d found my perfect supervisor!</p>

<p>Fast forward through a winter of persistent emails and video calls, and by summer, I’d lined up my a dream dissertation project in a topic that excited me at a world-leading university. A project marrying two fields; applying an AI technique to the domain mineral exploration for the critical battery metals. Determined to squeeze every drop of opportunity from this chance, I self-funded a 3-week trip to California.</p>

<h2 id="my-time-at-stanford">My Time at Stanford</h2>

<p>The experience was truly exceptional. AI research lab SISL, who provide AI technical support to Mineral-X, provided a warm welcome, offering me a desk in their office. As a master’s student working on only my second ever research project, being surrounded by Stanford PhDs and post-docs was incredibly special.</p>

<p>Having access to world experts in POMDPs (the AI technique I was using) proved invaluable. Their on-demand, in-person guidance significantly accelerated my progress. Beyond the office, they were lovely people too; kindly involving me in weekly ultimate frisbee, taking me to rock up and play soccer games with their friends, and freeing up time to go for coffee/beer to chat in a relaxed setting.</p>

<p>Beyond the academics I worked with directly, I met some incredible people too. During my first week, I was thrilled to discover Mineral-X were hosting their annual symposium during my second week on campus. This gathering brought together industry leaders, heads of data science teams, and recent PhD graduates from around the world, all in one place. The opportunity to engage directly with such a diverse group of experts in my field of interest was truly invaluable.</p>

<p>Besides the professional gains, June in California is somewhat superior to June in Edinburgh. Downtime was spent enjoying rounds at Stanford University Golf Course or supporting the Three Lions in the European Championships at a local English pub. To conclude the trip, I took a two-day Top Gear style drive drifting across both lanes of empty roads with amazing views in a convertible Mustang. I explored San Francisco’s bustling streets; crossed the Golden Gate Bridge; snapped pictures of Bay Area views; and rounded it off by drinking a bottle of red from Sonoma Valley in Sonoma Valley itself.</p>

<h2 id="reflection">Reflection</h2>

<p>I’ve ticked off a number of typical achievements in my life: from graduating school with the maximal grade of 3 A*s to being elected by my peers as 1st XI captain of the University of Warwick Men’s Football Club. But, sporting and academic achievements had never brought a sense of immense pride. After all, there is always someone outperforming you in academia and I’ve played alongside teammates far more talented footballers than me.</p>

<p>But, I know no one who had the initative to set up a dissertation project that aligned with their passions with an external supervisor based at a world-leading university they were not enrolled at. This time, my experience was entirely unique, and the sense of pride was striking.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A reflection on my dissertation project experience, in-particular my three week trip to California.]]></summary></entry></feed>